Music
I welcome you all to, Today’s lecture on “Dower Under Muslim law”.
Dower is one of the important components of marriage under Muslim law.
To understand the institution of Muslim marriage
one must learn the concept of dollar in detail.
Therefore in this lesson we will the discuss following issues relating to dower.
• Definition and Nature of Dower • Kinds of Dower • Fixation of Dower
• And Enforcement of Dower
Definition and Nature of Dower:
Unfortunately, the Islamic concept of Mehar has been widely misunderstood.
Those who are obsessed with the contractual
element in the Muslim concept of marriage,
regard it as “Consideration”.
Those who are more familiar with ‘dowry’ confuse it with the same.
The fact is that Mehar is neither ‘consideration’ nor dowry;
it has a unique position of its own.
To understand the Muslim concept of dower thoroughly
let us go through
some of the definitions of dower by eminent jurists of Islamic law.
According to Tyabji:
“Dower or mehar is a sum that becomes
payable by the husband to the wife on marriage,
either by agreement between the parties or by operation of law.”
Sir Abdur Rahim, defines it as,
‘dower is either a sum of money or other form of property
to which the wife becomes entitled by marriage.
It is an obligation imposed by law on the husband as a mark of respect for the wife’.
According to Baillie,
‘Dower is not exchange or consideration given by the man
to the woman for entering into the contract;
but an effect to the contract imposed by the law on her husband as a mark of respect
to its subject, the woman.’
Justice Mahmood defines dower as follows:
“Dower under the Mohammadan law
is a sum of money or other property promised by the husband to be paid or
delivered to the wife in consideration of the marriage,
even where no dower is expressly fixed or mentioned at the marriage ceremony,
the law confers the right of dower upon the wife.”
He further elaborates this point as under: -
“Dower may be regarded as a consideration for connubial intercourse
by way of analogy to the contract or sale.”
This observation is subject to serious doubt, as,
Sir Abdur Rahim correctly points out that;
“It is not a consideration in the modern sense of the term,
but an obligation imposed by the law upon the husband as a mark of respect to the wife.”
We know that if dower were a consideration it would always be prompt
and specified; but the law allows deferred dower
which is payable on the dissolution of marriage.
And even when it is not expressly fixed or mentioned at the marriage ceremony,
the law confers the right of dower upon the wife.
The law provides that dower can be fixed before, at the time of or after the marriage.
Dower is, therefore, different from consideration.
It is in fact an effect to the contract
imposed by law on the husband.
In Nasra Begum v. Rijwan Ali,
the court held that where there has been an agreement between the parties
at the time of their marriage with regard to the amount of dower
payable by the husband to the wife;
the payment of such dower amount becomes recoverable under agreement.
We know that the binding character of dower is that it has been divinely ordained.
The true nature of dower can be found in the Holy Quran itself.
Holy Quran uses the word Sudaqah for dower.
Sudaqah is a derivative of Sidiq, which means truth, regularity and friendship.
Dower in this Quranic sense is the symbol of truthfulness
and regularity of the friendship of husband and the wife.
Dower is to strengthen cooperation between the spouses and add to the dignity of women.
Kinds of dower:
We know that dower is payable whether the sum has been fixed
at the time of the marriage or not. Thus dower may be either specified or unspecified.
If the dower is specified then, again, it may be asked that when it is payable.
Thus we have the following kinds of dower in Islam.
1) Specified dower 2) Unspecified dower.
Specified dower may again be divided into:
i) Prompt dower. ii) Deferred dower.
Specified dower :
The dower, which the parties to the marriage may fix by stipulation,
is called specified dower.
Usually the dower is fixed at the time of marriage
and the Qazi performing the ceremony
enters the amount in the register;
or else there may be a regular contract called
Kabin-nama with numerous conditions.
The sum may be fixed either at the time of marriage or later.
The amount of dower may be fixed by the father if the son is minor
or of unsound mind and a father’s contract
on behalf of a minor son is binding on the minor.
In the Hanafi School the rule is that the dower as fixed by the father
is binding on the son and the father has no personal liability to pay it.
But among the Shias the rule is that if the son has no means to pay it,
the father is liable.
In a case of, SayedSabirHussain v. Farzand Hassan,
a Shia father had made himself surety for the payment of Mehar of his minor son,
thereafter, he died.
It was held that
the estate left by the deceased was liable for the payment of his son’s dower.
Accordingly in this case, each heir was made responsible
for a portion of the wife’s claim in proportion to the share
received by particular heir on distribution of the estate of the deceased.
Where the amount has been specified the husband will be compelled to pay whole of it,
however excessive it may seem to the court, having regard to the husband’s means.
Now we know that when dower is specified,
the question arises: At what time and in what proportion is the amount payable.
On this basis
dower has been classified as (i) Prompt and (ii) Deferred.
Prompt dower:
The technical term for prompt dower is Muajjal.
It is derived from a root meaning to hasten, to precede.
The term Muajjal, therefore, means that which has been hastened
or given a priority in point of time.
Prompt dower is payable
immediately after the marriage, if demanded by the wife.
The prompt dower may be realised by the wife at any time
before or after the consummation of the marriage.
The consummation of marriage or living with the husband is not necessary condition
for claiming it.
The demand should be specified and not conditional or ambiguous;
the payment of prompt dower may be postponed until there is an actual demand by the wife.
The wife may refuse to live with her husband and
admit her to sexual intercourse so long as the prompt dower is not paid.
If the husband sues her for restitution of conjugal rights before
sexual intercourse takes place,
non-payment of prompt dower
is a complete defence to the suit and the suit will be dismissed.
The heirs of a woman are entitled to it as forming part of her estate,
even though she might not have demanded it from her husband when alive.
Deferred Dower
The deferred dower is payable on the termination of marriage by death or divorce.
It has not become prompt by the demand of the wife
during the continuation of marriage.
But if there is any agreement as to the payment of
deferred dower earlier than the dissolution of the marriage,
such an agreement would be valid and binding.
The interest of the wife in the deferred dower
is a vested one
and not a contingent one.
It is not liable to be displaced by the happening of any event,
not even on her own death and as such her heir can claim the money if she dies.
Whether the dower shall be prompt or deferred
is primarily a matter of contract between the parties.
When there is such a contract such portion of dower
as is agreed to be prompt shall be prompt and the rest shall be deferred.
But when it has not been specified, there is a difference of opinion
as to whether the whole of it shall be presumed to be prompt or only a part of it.
Among Shias whole dower is presumed as prompt.
Under Hanafi School of thought whole of the dower may be promptly awarded,
but where the agreement is silent on the question,
the usage of the wives family is the main consideration
and in the absence of the proof of custom,
the presumption is that one half is prompt and the other half deferred,
and the proportion may be changed to suit individual cases.
Unspecified Dower
Unspecified dower is that dower not specified at the time of marriage or after divorce.
We know the obligation to pay dower is a legal responsibility on the part of her husband
and is not dependent upon any contract between the parties.
Where the dower is specified, it has to be paid accordingly.
But where the dower has not been settled at the time of marriage or after,
what are the principles upon which the amount of dower is to be determined?
The customary or proper dower of woman is to be fixed with reference
to the social position of her father’s family and her own personal qualification.
The Hedaya lays down the importance of the rule
that her age, beauty, fortune,
understanding and virtue must be taken into consideration.
The Islamic law, therefore, safeguards the rights of a wife
and attempts to ensure her an economic status consonant with her own social standing.
The husband may at any time after marriage increase the dower.
Likewise the wife has the power remitting the whole or
a portion of the dower in favour of her husband or his heirs.
Remission of dower is valid even if made without consideration,
provided the wife is a major and of sound mind.
In case of Ali v. Mohd, Madras High court
and in Mazmun-nisa v. Sirajuddin,
the High court of Patna
took the view that for the purposes of
remission of dower the age of majority should be reckoned
with under the Indian Majority Act,
i.e. the wife should have completed the age of eighteen years.
But in Qasim v. Kaniz,
the Allahabad High court expressed the opinion
that the age of majority is to be determined under Muslim law.
On a strict interpretation of the provisions of the Indian Majority Act
the view of the Allahabad High Court is correct,
but socially the better view is that of Patna and Madras High courts.
However, it is to be kept in mind,
the remission of a dower
must be made by the wife by her free consent.
The wife has also the power of reducing the amount of dower voluntarily.
The remission of her may also be conditional.
Thus in lieu of dower she may agree to receive annuity.
No acceptance of the remission of dower on the part of her  husband
or his heirs is necessary.
Enforcement of dower:
Now we would see the enforceability of dower.
It may be pointed out at the out set that the claim of the wife or
widow for unpaid portion of dower is an unsecured debt
due to her from her husband or his estate, respectively.
It ranks with unsecured debts and is actionable claim.
During her life time the wife can recover the debt herself
from the estate of the deceased.
Prompt dower can be enforced by refusal of conjugal rights.
When the prompt dower is not paid the wife can refuse conjugal rights to the husband
and non-payment of the prompt dower is a firm defence against the husband’s suit
for restitution of conjugal rights.
Not only this,
if on account of non-payment of dower,
the wife is living separately from her husband; he is bound to maintain her.
The wife can also file a suit against the husband for the recovery of the dower debt.
A wife can claim maintenance when living separately for non-payment of prompt Dower.
Deferred dower cannot be claimed on demand.
The non-payment of deferred dower by its very nature
cannot confer the right
of refusal on the wife to live with the husband.
Dower can be satisfied from the estate of deceased husband.
As we know that dower is a debt and the widow is entitled
along with other creditors of her deceased husband
to have it satisfied out of his estate.
The Supreme Court of India has made following observations about it in the case of,
Kapore Chand v. Kadar Unnissa,
“The wife is like any other creditor of the husband and cannot, therefore,
claim priority for the dower debt over other creditors;
The widow’s claim for dower debt has priority over the other claims of the other heirs.
The heirs of the deceased husband are not personally liable
for the dower debt of the widow.
The liability of an heir is to be
measured not by his interest in the estate but
by the assets which come into his hands.”
The widow’s right of retention:
We know that a widow can claim her dower even after death of her husband
out of his estate.
In this respect a right is given to the widow,
which is known as widow’s right of retention.
Literally speaking the right of retention is the act of withholding
what one has in his hands by virtue of some right,
as where a creditor
pays his own claim out of the debtor’s property
that comes into his hands as representative of the debtor.
Similarly the Muslim law gives the widow,
whose dower remains unpaid a special right to enforce her demand called as
“The Widow’s right of retention”.
This right subsists until her dower is paid off either by husband’s heirs
or is satisfied from the usufruct of the property that she holds.
Once she loses possession of her husband’s estate,
she loses her special right and is in no better position than an unsecured creditor.
Until it is paid she has a right to retain possession of the property
of which she has lawfully obtained possession.
The widow’s possession of her deceased husband’s estate is considered
to be lawfully held in lieu of dower
where the Mahr-nama provides for it or where she has been put into
such possession by her husband in lifetime
or by his heirs after death.
When the widow is already in possession of such property it is presumed
that it was lawfully obtained.
So far as the nature of widow’s right of retention is concerned
the following facts are to be taken into consideration.
1) Widow does not acquire any title to such property.
The widow’s right to retain the possession of the property in lieu of her dower is
not in the nature of regular charge mortgage or lien.
It is in essence a personal right as against heirs and creditors of the husband
to enforce her right.
2) The widow is responsible to other heirs, as she has to render accounts to them.
She is entitled to some reasonable compensation not only for the labour
and responsibility
imposed upon her for the proper management of the estate but also for bearing to
enforce her right of the dower debt
and such compensation is in the form of interest on the principal amount of the dower.
3) A widow cannot alienate such property.
The right of retention does not give the right to alienate property by sale,mortgage,
gift or otherwise for the satisfaction of her dower debt.
4) Heritability.
The widow’s right of retention is capable of descending to the heirs
of the widow on her death.
There was a diversity of judicial opinion as to whether the right to retain possession
of the property by a widow in lieu of dower was heritable.
But the conflict was finally resolved by the Supreme Court by holding that the
right to hold possession is heritable
This was held in
Kapoorchand v Kadar-un-nisa.
5)Transferability of the right.
So far as the widow is concerned she has a right to assign her dower debt,
but it is unsettled whether the right to hold and retain possession of her husband’s
estate till dower is paid, is transferable.
One view is that the right to hold and retain possession of the property being a
personal right cannot be transferred.
This view has been followed in, Abdul Samad v. Alim-ud-din.
The other view is that the right to hold and retain the possession of the property
as a security for the dower debt is property and therefore, transferable.
The widow’s right of retention when extinguishes:
The right is extinguished in following cases:
1) When the widow voluntarily gives up the possession,
which she once held in lieu of dower.
2) When the widow delivers possession of the property to third person.
3) When the dower debt, in respect of which the right is exercised,
is satisfied from the usufruct of the property.
4) When the dower debt in respect of which the right is exercised is satisfied by payment,
by the heirs of the deceased.
With these words, I conclude the Lecture.
Thank you very much.
Music